<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "docbookV4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Diameter_User_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;]>
<chapter id="i-Introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>Diameter is a computer networking protocol for AAA (Authentication, Authorization and Accounting) defined in RFC 3588. It is a successor to RADIUS (and its name is a reference to it, a diameter is twice the radius) offering the following advantages:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Reliable transport protocols (TCP or SCTP, not UDP)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Network or transport level security (IPSec or TLS)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Transition support for RADIUS, although Diameter is not fully compatible with RADIUS</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Larger address space for attribute-value pairs (AVPs) and identifiers (32 bits instead of 8 bits)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Client-server protocol, with exception of supporting some server-initiated messages as well</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Both stateful and stateless models can be used</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Dynamic discovery of peers (using DNS SRV and NAPTR)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Capability negotiation</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Supports application layer acknowledgments, defines failover methods and state machines (RFC 3539)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Error notification</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Better roaming support</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>More easily extended; new commands and attributes can be defined</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Aligned on 32-bit boundaries</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Basic support for user-sessions and accounting</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>It was designed in a way to be compatible with RADIUS but also to be easily extended with new use cases within AAA scenario and other IMS scenarios. Extensions are called &quot;Applications&quot;.</para>
  <para>Each application introduces new types of messages,  AVP codes, and state machines.  The Message and AVP codes are assigned by the IANA.  Furthermore,  each application has its own application ID and vendor ID that is used to distinguish between applications. In addition, application code is used to signal to other peers which  operations are supported by connecting peer (Capabilities Exchange).</para>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="section-Message_Format.xml" encoding="UTF-8"/>
</chapter>
